A Guide to the Records of the Secretary of the Commonwealth, Extradition Requisition and Rendition Files of Governor Terry McAuliffe, 2014-2017
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Secretary of the Commonwealth, Extradition Requisition and Rendition Files of Governor Terry McAuliffe, 2014-2017
The Library of Virginia
52209
14 cu. ft.(14 boxes)
Virginia. Secretary of the Commonwealth.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The records must be reviewed by staff for privacy protected information before serving. Extradition requisition and rendition letters from the Governor(s) may be served, however records including privacy protected information such as social security numbers may not. Privacy protected and confidential information is restricted from public access for 75 years per code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Restricted records were not removed from the collection. Types of information and records may include, but are not limited to: social security numbers, Department of Corrections inmate material, fingerprint files, mediation and settlement discussions, and attorney-client privileged material.
Acquisition Information
Office of the Secretary of the Commonwealth, Patrick Henry Building, 1111 East Broad Street, Richmond, VA 23219, transferred 24 January 2018.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Office of the Secretary of the Commonwealth evolved from the yearly Secretary of the Colony. Early Secretaries were elected by the public. An Act of the General Assembly in 1920 changed the election to a joint vote of the General Assembly. In a 1930 Act the duties of the Secretary were redefined with the Secretary of the Commonwealth serving as the ex officio secretary of the Governor, as custodian of many official State records, and as keeper of the Greater and Lesser Seals of the Commonwealth. The office of the Secretary has gradually acquired other functions, such as: service of out-of-state civil process; appointment and regulation of notaries public; and registration and oversight of lobbyists. The Office became a gubernatorial appointment subsequent to a 1958 Act of the Assembly. The Secretary of the Commonwealth is under the jurisdiction of the Governor's Office.
In Virginia, the provisions governing extradition procedures are set forth in Sections 19.2-84 through 19.2-118 of the Code of Virginia. Requisitions and extraditions are handled by the Secretary of the Commonwealth.
Extradition is the legal surrender of an alleged criminal, apprehended in one jurisdiction, to another state, country or other government unit for trial. The accused can be extradited when he or she is charged with any punishable offense in the demanding jurisdiction. Extraditions are both received and requested by the governor. A requisition warrant documents Virginia's request of another state to return a fugitive to Virginia's jurisdiction. A rendition documents another state's request of Virginia to return a fugitive to the requesting state's jurisdiction.
Scope and Content
A typical requisition file contains an application from the Commonwealth's Attorney, a formal request by the Governor for extradition, and the Governor's request of one or more law enforcement officers to retrieve the fugitive. The Commonwealth's Attorney's application usually includes: copies of the indictment or arrest warrant with supporting affidavits and a statement of facts in support of a Governor's Warrant. Some files include a photograph of the subject of the requisition.
A typical rendition file contains a formal request for extradition from another state's governor, correspondence from the Office of the Attorney General to the Office of the Governor concerning the extradition request, and a copy of the notice of extradition sent by the Secretary of the Commonwealth to the wanted individual. The request for extradition usually includes: copies of the indictment or arrest warrant with supporting affidavits and an appointment of agent by the Governor. Some applications may include a photograph of the fugitive. Also included in each files is a Rendition Fact Sheet completed by the Secretary of the Commonwealth. The Rendition Fact Sheet lists date received, jurisdiction, fugitive's name and address, attorney's name and address, date charged as a fugitive, disposition of fugitive warrant, next scheduled court appearance on fugitive warrant, fugitive status (in custody or out on bond), list of pending Virginia charges and disposition and contact information for requester.
The records from this collection must be reviewed by staff for personal and medical privacy protected information before serving. Both requisitions and renditions may include privacy protected information such as social security and fingerprints, and case, penitentiary, and arrest records.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I: Renditions
Series II: Requisitions
The files are arranged chronologically by year and by month therein, with the exception for 2014 in each of the two series. Renditions and Requisitions for 2014 are arranged alphabetically, and this original arrangement was maintained by the processing archivist.
Related Material
The Governor Terry McAuliffe Administration Web Archive Collection, 2014-2018
The Records of the Secretary of the Commonwealth, Extradition Requisition and Rendition Files of Governor Robert F. McDonnell, 2010-2013 Collection
Contents List
- Series I: Extradition Requisitions and Renditions: Renditions, 2014-2017., Extent: 4 cu. ft. (4 boxes) (Box 1-4)
  - 2014
    - A-Z (Box 1)
  - 2015
    - January-December (A-Z) (Box 2)
  - 2016
    - January-December (A-W) (Box 3)
  - 2017
    - January-December (A-Y) (Box 4)
- Series II: Extradition Requisitions and Renditions: Requisitions, 2014-2017., Extent: 10 cu. ft. (10 boxes) (Box 5-14)
  - 2014
    - A-L (Box 5)
    - M-Z (Box 6)
  - 2015
    - January-July (A-T) (Box 7)
    - January-July (T-Z); August-December (A-Z) (Box 8)
  - 2016
    - January- June (A-R) (Box 9)
    - January-June (R-Y); July- December (A-M) (Box 10)
    - July-December (M-Z) (Box 11)
  - 2017
    - January- June (A-S) (Box 12)
    - January-June (S-Y); July-December (A-K) (Box 13)
    - July-December (K-Y) (Box 14)